So, the global movement of
decolonization after World War got uh
real complicated by the Cold War and I
reckon you need me to Heim explain it up
for you real nice. So, if you're ready
to get them brain cows milked, let's get
to it. Okay, now the first thing you
need to know about this topic is going
to set the context for all the
decolonization complications and the
proxy wars that I'm going to tell you
about in a minute. And the context is
this, as the Cold War rivalry spread and
grew more intense, debates about nuclear
proliferation grew equally intense. So,
recall that one of the key features of
the Cold War was a constantly escalating
arms race between the United States and
the Soviet Union. In no small part of
that build-up was the proliferation of
stronger and more powerful nuclear
bombs, not to mention a significant
increase in spending to beef up the
military itself. However, President
Eisenhower sniffed out a fatal flaw in
the system. He called it the
military-industrial complex and he
warned Americans against its influence
in his farewell speech at the end of his
second term. The idea was that the
military and the defense industry that
made all the weapons and munitions were
becoming too tightly dependent on one
another. In other words, the military
needed munitions and therefore shelled
out enormous amounts of taxpayer dollars
via Congress to private corporations who
built those munitions and those
companies got rich off the exchange. So,
Eisenhower warned that because the
tensions of the Cold War perpetuated
this relationship, America could get to
the point and perhaps already was at the
point in which this relationship became
so vital to the economy that it could
send Americans into poverty and
ultimately dictate the kinds of policies
that govern the entire country. So, in
light of that, during his presidency
Eisenhower took steps to limit this
relationship by promoting what he called
the New Look. So, since
boots-on-the-ground military engagements
were enormously costly, Eisenhower
emphasized the production of a growing
nuclear arsenal, which was on the whole
cheaper than military intervention and
arguably more destructive in its use.
And while it's true that New Look
policies did save some money, they also
created an altogether different problem,
which was in some ways more precarious
than the military-industrial complex
itself. First of all, the scaling of
America's nuclear arsenal simply
encouraged the Soviet Union to do the
same. Second, because both sides
understood that deploying these weapons
would result in mutual assured
destruction, the New Look strategy
emphasized the extremely risky strategy
of brinkmanship. In other words, if
tensions between the US and the Soviets
heated up, the only guarantee to avoid
nuclear war was for both sides to
possess an enormous stockpile of nuclear
weapons. And in that way, they might
bring each other to the very brink of
war just hoping that the other side
would back down in the face of a
superior nuclear arsenal because, you
know, mutual assured destruction and
all. And that, to put it mildly, was uh
scary. Okay, so now that you have the
context, let's talk about how
decolonization only intensified the
tensions that I just mentioned. But
first, let me explain to you what in the
fresh heck decolonization is anyway. So,
as you'll know that remember, Europeans
have been building their empires for
centuries, but the two World Wars
created an intense turning point that
ultimately led to the dissolution of
those empires, and that process was
known as decolonization. So, as it
turned out, the European imperial powers
that fought in World War I called up
millions of troops from their colonial
holdings to help them fight the war. And
although they really had no choice in
the matter, many colonial troops fought
for their imperial parents' cause hoping
that their sacrifices would be honored
with a greater degree of self-rule or
even independence. And that hope was
further stoked by Woodrow Wilson's
prodigious mouth-flapping about the
importance of self- determination for
countries after the war. But here's
where I tell you that didn't really
happen. But that's fine because there
was a Second World War, and again,
colonial troops fought for their
imperial parents' cause. But this time,
after the war was over and there
appeared to be no clear intention of the
imperial countries to grant independence
to their colonies, massive anti-imperial
movements broke out across the world.
And so, after 1945, these developments
would lead to a worldwide process of
decolonization which broke apart
colonial empires and created something
like 80 new states on the world map. And
that's great, right? Like what a relief.
Like all those nations across the world
that had for so long been hobbled by the
lash of imperial policy are now
independent and free to pursue policies
that will advance their own
self-interest. Ah, crap. Here comes the
Cold War to take a giant geopolitical
dump on such blossoming political
desires. So, remember that one of the
major features of the Cold War was an
ideological struggle between the
democratic capitalism of the United
States and the authoritarian communism
of the Soviet Union. And that means when
decolonization got underway, all those
brand new nations got the two
superpowers in a proper feeding frenzy
to win them to their respective
ideology. However, some groups and
individuals in these newly forming
states refused to be pawns in this
global conflict, which in many ways
would make them dependent on more
powerful nations, which is exactly the
situation they had just escaped in their
recent colonial past. And that's when
the Non-Aligned Movement was born in
1955. In the beginning, it was a group
of 29 African and Asian heads of state
who described themselves as non-aligned
in order to communicate that they
refused to be controlled by the global
conflict between these two superpowers.
However, some leaders of non-aligned
nations were also shrewd and they knew
how to take advantage of this Cold War
rivalry. Like by feigning support for
one side or the other, some non-aligned
states were able to gain weapons and
resources that they needed for their own
defense and development. But other
independent nations weren't so lucky and
got altogether sucked up into this Cold
War rivalry. But before I tell you about
that, let me just say that if you
yourself are non-aligned with the
reality of getting a bad score in your
APUSH exam in May, then you might want
to check out my APUSH Heimler Review
Guide. He's got everything you need to
study as fast as possible and no small
amount of sass to go with it, and that
link is down in the description. Anyway,
let me tell you about two conflicts that
should not have been as consequential as
they were, but you know, the Cold War
blew them all out of proportion. So,
over in Africa, let me tell you briefly
about the Angolan Civil War. So, in
1975, Angolans had won their
independence through armed struggle
against the Portuguese, but almost
immediately a civil war broke out among
various rival ethnic groups as they each
sought the power to rule. And so, the US
and its allies supported the
non-communist groups, while the Soviet
Union and its allies supported the
communist groups. And what might have
been a much more subdued and brief
struggle for power became a years-long
war with many more casualties thanks to
the involvement of the Soviets and the
Americans. Regardless, in the end, the
communist forces won and assumed power.
But then that ever pervasive Cold War
rivalry also slapped the Middle East in
the face. And here, let me tell you
about Egypt. So, for the first few
decades of the Cold War, Egypt had
developed a close relationship with the
Soviet Union. However, by the 1970s,
that relationship was cooling and a new
administration in Egypt was interested
in pursuing a closer relationship with
the United States. And this is kind of a
big deal because the rest of the Middle
East was home to massive deposits of oil
on which the United States was becoming
increasingly dependent and having a
friend like Egypt would help American
policy makers slake their undying thirst
for that sweet black gold. Therefore,
seeing an opportunity to weaken Soviet
influence in the region, President Jimmy
Carter mediated the Camp David Accords,
which strengthened ties between the
United States and Egypt, which was a
geopolitical win for the US Cold War
effort. And hey, maybe at this point
you're worried that Latin America didn't
get in on this coercive Cold War chess
match, but fear not, my dear people,
because the Soviets and Americans were
positively giddy about moving into those
nations as well. So, that wave of
independence movements and
decolonization that I just mentioned
also had serious implications for US
foreign policy in Latin America. And as
leaders in countries like Cuba and
Guatemala nationalized their countries'
assets, the US was compelled to
intervene in order to protect its
economic interests and prevent the
spread of communism, and I'll give you
two particularly juicy examples. First,
let's talk about Guatemala. So, in 1954,
the newly elected socialist leader of
Guatemala, Jacobo Arbenz, claimed
Guatemalan ownership of several hundred
thousand acres of farmland owned by the
United Fruit Company. And if you recall,
that was an American-owned corporation.
And if there's one thing that could put
American policy-makers in a proper huff,
it was countries trying to take back
what Americans already took from them.
Because that's just rude. Anyway, what
seriously complicated the situation was
the several high-ranking officials in
the Eisenhower administration were part
owners in the United Fruit Company and
therefore stood to lose a lot of money
by this stupid socialist and a stupid
socialist policies. But outwardly, these
officials convinced Eisenhower that
Arbenz's actions threatened American
possession of the Panama Canal, which
was a vital waterway for international
trade. And therefore, Eisenhower went
ahead and permitted the CIA to organize
a plot to overthrow the socialist Arbenz
regime. And in the end, the operation
was successful, and they went ahead and
installed an extreme right-wing military
dictator who protected American
interests in the United Fruit Company
and in the Panama Canal. And in the
second big example of Cold War rivalry
extending into Latin America happened in
Cuba. So, the success of the Guatemala
operation got the Eisenhower
administration thinking that maybe they
should go ahead and try it again. And
that's because in 1959, a socialist
leader named Fidel Castro rose to power
in Cuba after leading a successful
rebellion that ousted the
American-backed Cuban president. And one
of Castro's first moves was to gain
control over all of Cuba's economic
assets, significant portions of which
were controlled by American
corporations, so here we go again. So,
in 1960, Eisenhower again authorized the
CIA to conduct a secret operation to
overthrow Castro and install an
American-friendly leader. However,
Eisenhower left office before the plan
could be executed, and so it fell to
John F. Kennedy. Now, Kennedy approved
the plan and set into motion the Bay of
Pigs invasion in 1961, which, unlike the
Guatemalan operation, ultimately was a
giant honking disaster. Long story
short, the CIA had trained about 1,500
Cuban nationals who opposed Castro and
sent them to invade Cuba on the
assumption that many thousands more
disgruntled Cubans would join them. And
as it turned out, that did not, in fact,
happen. In seeking to keep US
involvement a secret, Kennedy provided
no military reinforcements for the small
force of invading Cubans. The result was
that Castro's forces slaughtered the
invaders, and the relations between Cuba
and the United States sank to a new low
as Castro developed a much closer
relationship with the Soviet Union.
Well, okay, you can click here to watch
all my other Unit 4 videos, or you can
click here to grab my A push Heimler
review guide, which has everything you
need to study as fast as possible. I'm
glad you came around, and I'll catch you
on the flip-flop. Heimler out.